A Guide to the Richmond (Va.) Office of the City Engineer, Records, 1809-1975
Library of Virginia
- Series I. Architectural drawings and plans, 1809-1975.
  - Street - [Plan of area between Cary, Plum, Main, and Morris streets, 30-A-2, n.d., Dimensions: 16 x 38-1/4 in. - 41 x 97 cm.; Scale: 1" = 40'; Media: India ink, pencil, red ink, and blue ink on heavy paper; Sheets: 1 (Folder 72)
  - Street - Plan / of / Roads in Grove /East of Reservoir, 65-B-5, n.d., Dimensions: 38-1/2 x 37-1/2 in. - 98 x 95 cm.; Scale: 1" = 20'; Media: India ink and yellow ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 65)
  - Street - [Map of Catherine Street between Monroe Street and Hancock Street], 17-A-5, n.d., Dimensions: 12-1/4 x 75-3/4 in. - 31 x 79 cm.; Scale: 1" = 20'; Media: Pencil, India ink, and red ink on heavy paper; Sheets: 1 (Folder 68)
  - Street - Valley Road [Plan and profile of road in area of Bacon's Quarter Branch bridge], 122-C-2, n.d., Dimensions: 25 x 37-3/4 in. - 63 x 96 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Pencil, India ink, pencil, and yellow ink on linen; Sheets: 2 (Folder 65)
  - Street - [Map of Brook Road from Calhoun St. to Broad St.], 2-A-2, n.d., Dimensions: 11-1/4 x 53 in. - 28 x 135 cm.; Scale: None; Media: India ink and red ink on paper with cloth backing; Sheets: 1 (Folder 69)
  - Street - [Profile and plan of Mechanicsville Turnpike between Redd and Venable Streets showing names of property owners], 66-A-2, n.d., Dimensions: 12-1/2 x 37 in. - 31 x 94 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Pencil, India ink, and yellow ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 77)
  - Street - [Map showing Richmond streets and drainage mains (?) between Lombardy and 3rd., 56-B-5, n.d., Dimensions: 43 x 25-3/4 in. - 109 x 65 cm.; Scale: None; Media: India ink, red ink, and blue ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 65)
  - Street - Plat Showing / Proposed Alley in Block Bounded by / Main, Cary, 8th and 9th Streets, 11090-C-1, n.d., Dimensions: 24 x 21-3/4 in. - 61 x 55 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Blueprints (heavily damaged); Sheets: 2 (Folder 76)
  - Street - [Topographic study of hillside in area of Broad, 21st., and Grace streets], 54-B-5, n.d., Dimensions: 18 x 39-3/4 in. - 46 x 101 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Pencil, India ink, red ink, and yellow ink on paper with fabric backing; Sheets: 1 (Folder 65)
  - Street - [Grade profiles], 84-C-2b, n.d., Dimensions: 30 x 12 in. - 76 x 31 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Pencil on heavy graph paper; Sheets: 1 (Folder 64)
  - Street - Proposed Avenue 104 ft. wide - 4360 ft. long from S. line Cary to Center of Broad St., 1-A-5, n.d., Dimensions: 8-1/2 x 86 in. - 22 x 218 cm.; Scale: None; Media: India ink and red ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 69)
  - Street - Encroachments in - E Street / and report to hall [found on verso of one fragment], 2-A-5, n.d., Dimensions: Various; Scale: None; Media: Ink on heavy paper with pencil notations. In nine pieces - heavily damaged and brittle with multiple repairs; Sheets: 9 (Folder 69)
  - Street - Plan / of proposed New Street on the / South Side of the Dock from the / Creek to 23rd St., 6-A-5, n.d., Dimensions: 16 x 48 in. - 41 x 121 cm.; Scale: 1" = 50'; Media: India ink, red ink, and blue ink on heavy paper; Sheets: 1 (Folder 69)
  - Streetcar - Sections / of / Street Railway / Tracks., 1-C-2, 1894, Dimensions: 18-1/2 x 51 in. - 47 x 130 cm.; Scale: Full scale; Media: India ink, brown ink, and washes on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
  - Streetcar - Map / of / Present Car Tracks and Proposed Changes on Broad St. West of Smith St., 23-A-2, 1895, Dimensions: 16 x 69 in. - 41 x 175 cm.; Scale: 1" = 40'; Media: India ink and red ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
    Drawn By: City Engineer's Office, Richmond, Va.
  - Streetcar - Proposed Side Poles, 15-B-4, 1895, Dimensions: 36-1/2 x 18 in. - 93 x 46 cm.; Scale: 1" = 1'; Media: Blueprint with ink notations; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
    Drawn By: W. E. Cutshaw, City Engineer
  - Streetcar - Approval Plan / for / Setting Span and Anchor Poles / First Street Branch Line / Richmond Traction Co., 25-B-4, 1896, Dimensions: 30-1/2 x 45-1/4 in. - 77 x 115 cm.; Scale: 1" = 100'; Media: India ink, red ink, and blue ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
  - Streetcar - Map Showing / Proposed Temporary Arrangement of Tracks / on Broad St. west of Belvidere, 23-A-2, 1896, Dimensions: 16-1/4 x 58-3/4 in. - 41 x 147 cm.; Scale: 1" = 40'; Media: India ink and red ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
    Drawn By: [Approval signatures of officials]
  - Streetcar - Drawing of Center Poles / to be used by / The Richmond Traction Co. / on / Broad St. bet. Jail Alley & Robinson St., 15-B-4, 1896, Dimensions: 34 x17 in. - 86 x 43 cm.; Scale: 3/4" = 1'; Media: Blueprint; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
    Drawn By: [Approval signatures of City and streetcar officials]
  - Streetcar - Map / of / Proposed Track Crossings / on Broad St. west of Belvidere St., 23-A-2, 1896, Dimensions: 16-1/4 x 60 in. - 41 x 152 cm.; Scale: 1" = 40'; Media: India ink and red ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
  - Streetcar - Map / of / Broad St. from 34th St. to Boulevard / showing Center Line for Car Tracks, 8-C-2, 1896, Dimensions: 24-3/4 x 64 in. - 60 x 162 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: India ink and red ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 79)
    Drawn By: Approved / W. E. Cutshaw / City Engineer
  - Streetcar - Map of / Richmond and Manchester / showing / The Richmond Passenger and Power Co's Tracks / and / The Progress of Rehabilitation up to this Date, 14-C-2, 1901, Dimensions: 19-1/4 x 28-1/2 in. - 49 x 73 cm.; Scale: 1" = 1000'; Media: India ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
    Drawn By: H. P. Beck - Del.
  - Streetcar - Standard for Tie Spacing / for / Street Railways, 25-A-2, 1909, Dimensions: 15 x 42-1/4 in. - 38 x 107 cm.; Scale: 1" = 1'; Media: India ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
  - Streetcar - [Plans and elevations of two streetcar waiting sheds at Main and Harrison streets and Laurel and Main streets], 58-B-1, 1909, Dimensions: 21 x 25-1/2 in. - 53 x 64 cm.; Scale: None; Media: India ink and red ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
  - Streetcar - Map Showing Proposed Layout of / Car Sheds, Shops, and Etc. / Near the Reservoir, 28-A-4, 1909, Dimensions: 41-1/2 x 34-1/2 in. - 105 x 88 cm.; Scale: 1" = 40'; Media: Blueprints; Sheets: 2 (Folder 78)
    Drawn By: Virginia Railway and Power Co.
  - Streetcar - Virginia Railway and Power Co. / Map Showing / Electric Railway Lines / in / Richmond & Vicinity, 20-D-4, 1911, Dimensions: 33 x 38-1/2 in. - 84 x 98 cm.; Scale: 1" = 1000'; Media: Blueline print with colored inks; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
    Drawn By: Virginia Raillery and Power Co.
  - Streetcar - Proposed Addition to / Special Work Layout At 7th. & Broad / and / Proposed Special Work At / 7th. & Franklin and 8th. And Franklin, 65-A-1, 1912, Dimensions: 14 x 13-3/4 in. - 35 x 38 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Blueprint with ink notations; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
    Drawn By: Virginia Railway & Power Co.
  - Streetcar - This Plan Shows Method of Construction / of Track by the Virginia Railway & / Power Company, 60-B-4, 1912, Dimensions: 16-3/4 x 34 in. - 42 x 86 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Blueprint with colored inks mounted on board; Sheets: 1 (Folder 79)
  - Streetcar - Virginia Railway and Power Co. / Plan of Track Extensions / to be Made Under the Terms of an Ordinance of the / City of Richmond, 63-C-2, 1913, Dimensions: 37 x 61 in. - 79 x 201 cm.; Scale: 1" = 100'; Media: Pencil, India ink, and red ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
    Drawn By: [Approval signatures of Richmond City Engineer and engineer of railway company]
  - Streetcar - Plan Showing Elevations of / Curbs and Street Railway / Tracks on Broad Street / from W. S. of 3rd to W. S. of Foushee St., 85-A-2, 1913, Dimensions: 16-1/2 x 42 in. - 42 x 107 cm.; Scale: None; Media: India ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 79)
  - Streetcar - Richmond, Va. / Plan of the Boulevard from / Broad St. to the R. F. P. R. R. / Showing the Proposed Arrangement of / Street Railway Tracks, 69-A-1, 1915, Dimensions: 35-1/4 x 13-1/4 in. - 89 x 33 cm.; Scale: 1" = 100'; Media: Pencil and India ink on tracing paper; Sheets: 1 (Folder 79)
  - Streetcar - Map Showing / Street Railway Tracks Richmond & Vicinity, 14-C-2, 1923, Dimensions: 36 x 40 in. - 91 x 102 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Blueprint; Sheets: 3 (Folder 78)
  - Streetcar - Proposed Addition / To Special Work Layout / At And Near 1st. And Broad Sts., 65-A-1, n.d., Dimensions: 25-1/2 x 15 in. - 65 x 38 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Blueprint; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
  - Streetcar - [Plan of streetcar poles on 18th, Venable and Q streets route and Robinson Street route], 21-B-4, n.d., Dimensions: 23 x 44-1/2 in. - 58 x 113 cm.; Scale: 1" = 200'; Media: India ink and red ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
    Drawn By: [approval signatures of City and streetcar officials]
  - Streetcar - Proposed Centre pole [design for lamp pole and streetcar line support], 15-B-4, n.d., Dimensions: 25-3/4 x 14 in. - 65 x 35 cm.; Scale: 3/4" = 1'; Media: India ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
  - Streetcar - Map / of / Streets / between Hollywood Cemetery and Broad St. / and Harrison and 2nd Sts. / Showing Routes of Street Cars., 27-A-5, n.d., Dimensions: 54-1/4 x 37-3/4 in. - 96 x 95 cm.; Scale: 1" = 100'; Media: India ink, red ink, and yellow ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 78)
  - Streetcar - Map No. 1 / Showing Proposed Changes in Tracks, 20-D-4, n.d., Dimensions: 31-1/2 x 41 -1/2 in. - 80 x 105 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Blueprint; Sheets: 2 (Folder 78)
  - Tunnel - Extension of Church Hill Tunnel / From East Portal 125 Ft. East / Plan for Plain Concrete Arch, 51-C-2, 1912, Dimensions: 25-3/4 x 27-1/4 in. - 66 x 69 cm.; Scale: 1/2" = 1'; Media: Pencil and India ink on linen; Sheets: 2 (Folder 80)
  - Tunnel - Section Through Axis of Arch, 51-C-2f, 1913, Dimensions: 17 x 28-1/2 in. - 43 x 73 cm.; Scale: 1/2" = 1'; Media: piiol; Sheets: 1 (Folder 80)
  - Tunnel - Extension of Church Hill Tunnel / Plan of Concrete Portal, 51-C-2c, 1913, Dimensions: 35-1/2 x 31 in. - 90 x 79 cm.; Scale: 1/2" = 1'; Media: Pencil and India ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 80)
  - Tunnel - Extension of Church Hill Tunnel / Concrete Portal, 51-C-2d, 1913, Dimensions: 24-3/4 x 48-1/4 in. - 63 x 122 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: India ink on linen with red ink notations; Sheets: 1 (Folder 80)
  - Tunnel - Sketch / Showing Location of C. & O. Ry. Track and / Retaining Walls at East End Church Hill Tunnel, 51-C-2b, 1913, Dimensions: 10 x 22-1/2 in. - 25 x 57 cm.; Scale: 1" = 20'; Media: piiol; Sheets: 1 (Folder 80)
  - Tunnel - Extension of Church Hill Tunnel / Richmond, Va., 51-C-2, 1913, Dimensions: 16-1/2 x 28 in. - 42 x 71 cm.; Scale: None; Media: Blueprint with red pencil notations; Sheets: 1 (Folder 80)
  - Tunnel - Tunnel System Connecting With the Central Power Plant, Y-7389, 1939, Dimensions: 23-1/2 x 36 in. - 60 x 91 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: Blueprints; Sheets: 8 (Folder Roll 17)
    Drawn By: Carneal, Johnston & Wirght / Baskervill & Son / Richmond, Va.
  - Tunnel - Situation Plan C. & O. Ry. Tunnel Beneath Church Hill - Richmond, VA., P-692, 1953, Dimensions: 30 x 42-1/4 in. - 76 x 107 cm.; Scale: 1" = 100'; Media: India ink on linen; Sheets: 1 (Folder 80)
    Drawn By: Department of Public Works / Richmond, Virginia
  - Tunnel - [Plan of eastern portal and surrounding area], 51-C-2e, n.d., Dimensions: 19-1/4 x 31 in. - 49 x 79 cm.; Scale: 1" = 100'; Media: piiol; Sheets: 1 (Folder 80)
  - Tunnel - Profile of ground Between the Fredericksburg & Petersburg Railroads / Showing the several grades and a Tunnel through Gambles Hill to form a connection, 22-A-1, n.d., Dimensions: 14-1/2 x 56-1/2 in. - 37 x 143 cm.; Scale: Various; Media: India ink and colored inks with pencil notations on paper with cardboard backing; Sheets: 1 (Folder 80)
    Drawn By: John Grant C. E.
- Series II. Plats, 1815-1866.
  Partial internal index.
  - Plat Book A, 1826-1866
  - Plat Book B 1815-1862